<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the Kings most excellent Majesty giving thanks for the royal declaration for liberty of conscience</title>
            <author>Cheesman, Thomas, fl. 1688-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08741</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3775B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R173821</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">61296929</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 61296929</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180505</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08741)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180505)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2831:38)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the Kings most excellent Majesty giving thanks for the royal declaration for liberty of conscience</title>
                  <author>Cheesman, Thomas, fl. 1688-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Janeway,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: "Thomas Cheisman a nonconformist minister, living at Ilsley in Berkshire."</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701 --  Poetry.</term>
               <term>Liberty of conscience --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:180505:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE King's Moſt Excellent Majeſty, Giving Thanks for His ROYAL DECLARATION FOR LIBERTY of CONSCIENCE.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>NO Monument, tho made of Solid Gold,</l>
               <l>As high as the proud Pyramids of old;</l>
               <l>No Marble Statue, reaching to the Skies,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Great CAESAR</hi> can do more to Eternize</l>
               <l>Your Memory, and make Your Royal Name</l>
               <l>Sound in the Trumpet of Immortal Fame,</l>
               <l>Through all ſucceeding Ages, than this thing</l>
               <l>So wiſely brought to paſs; the World ſhall ring</l>
               <l>With loud Applauſe, and Children yet unborn,</l>
               <l>Your worth ſhall ſtrive to ſet forth and adorn:</l>
               <l>While with Triumphant Joy they Celebrate</l>
               <l>The Day, when firſt You wore the Crown in State.</l>
               <l>That happy Monarch, in whoſe Nuptial Bed,</l>
               <l>The White Roſe grew united to the Red,</l>
               <l>Shall not ſo famous in our Annals ſtand,</l>
               <l>As You for making Peace throughout the Land.</l>
               <l>And Your Progenitors, which did advance</l>
               <l>Victorious Enſigns in the Heart of <hi>France,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Never ſuch Honour, nor ſuch Glory won,</l>
               <l>As by this <hi>Declaration</hi> You have done.</l>
               <l>Mercy in its ſoft Boſom carries Charms,</l>
               <l>More Potent to prevail, than war-like Arms;</l>
               <l>And Kings, like God himſelf, appear to Shine,</l>
               <l>When they are Deckt with Clemency Divine.</l>
               <l>No Thoughts can reach, much leſs can Words declare,</l>
               <l>What the ſad Miſeries of the Nation were;</l>
               <l>Till like a wiſe Phyſitian, You had found</l>
               <l>This Soveraign Balm, to heal our bleeding Wound.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Orpheus</hi> they ſay, in Muſick had ſuch Skill,</l>
               <l>That he could Tame fierce Tygers at his will;</l>
               <l>The Hound would court the Hare, and Lyons play</l>
               <l>With tender Lambs, forgetful of their Prey.</l>
               <l>This Fable is made good by You in part,</l>
               <l>For cruel Men that have the hardeſt Heart,</l>
               <l>If they but liſten to your Counſel Sage,</l>
               <l>'Twill calm their Spirit, and reſtrain their Rage.</l>
               <l>Were I a Poet, whoſe rich Fancy ſtood</l>
               <l>Up to the Chin in the <hi>Caſtallian</hi> Flood:</l>
               <l>Yet my inlarged Soul could not expreſs</l>
               <l>The thouſandth Part of <hi>England</hi>'s Thankfulneſs.</l>
               <l>Nor might this Verſe of mine preſume to ſhow</l>
               <l>To You, how much both Church and State muſt owe</l>
               <l>For ſuch Tranſcendant Grace, by which You have</l>
               <l>Raiſed up many from their very Grave,</l>
               <l>Which there lay Dead in Law, and Slain before,</l>
               <l>But now Your Bounty doth to Life reſtore;</l>
               <l>You give them Reſt and Safety, and have broke,</l>
               <l>From off their Necks, the Iron-Galling Yoke.</l>
               <l>Freedom for Conſcience will create a Heaven</l>
               <l>Here upon Earth; there's nothing can be given</l>
               <l>More Sweet and Precious; this, and this alone,</l>
               <l>Ev'n in the Hearts of Men, ſets up a Throne</l>
               <l>For Princes there to Reign, and win ſuch Love,</l>
               <l>As may their ſtrongeſt Guard and Fortreſs prove.</l>
               <l>What tho Self-ſeeking Men at this Repine,</l>
               <l>Such as can gladly Feaſt and ſwim in Wine,</l>
               <l>While others ſwim in Tears, and ſtill would fain</l>
               <l>By publick Loſs, increaſe their private Gain:</l>
               <l>Yet all true Friends of Peace muſt needs rejoyce,</l>
               <l>And give You Thanks with One conſenting Voice.</l>
               <l>Upon Your Sacred Head, let Heaven pour</l>
               <l>The choiceſt Bleſſings in a fruitful Show'r.</l>
               <l>Let all Succeſs and Happineſs attend</l>
               <l>Your Glorious Reign, and Crown it to</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Cheiſman <hi>a Nonconformiſt Miniſter, living at</hi> Ilſley <hi>in</hi> Berkſhire.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Janeway</hi> in <hi>Queens-Head-Alley,</hi> in <hi>Pater-Noſter-Rom.</hi> MDCLXXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
